Guide to the Elmer Louis Kayser papers, 1824-1985 MS0245.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Elmer Louis Kayser papers
1824-2002
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Kayser, Elmer Louis
MS0245.UA
21.5 Linear Feet
Elmer Louis Kayser (1896-1985) came to The George Washington University as a student in 1914 and stayed until his death 1985. He was an institution unto himself, and author of two books chronicling the history of GW: Bricks Without Straw: The Evolution of George Washington University (1970) and A Medical Center The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University (1973). He also wrote The Grand Social Enterprise; A Study of Jeremy Bentham in his Relation to Liberal Nationalism (1932) and A Manual of Ancient History (1937). Kayser was professor of European history from 1917-67 when he assumed the role of professor emeritus. He was also the University Historian from 1962-85. Collection includes correspondence, course lectures, notes, notes on fraternities, speeches, student papers, publications, Mt. Vernon Seminary materials, WTOP Radio "Today in History" broadcasts, professional association memberships, photographs, a video cassette, and two framed pieces of realia. The materials range in date from 1824-1985. These items all relate to the personal and professional life of Elmer Kayser.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Acquired through donation of Mr. and Mrs. Arthur Hallett Page IV, 1985.
Biographical Note
Elmer Louis Kayser (1896-1985) came to The George Washington University as a student in 1914 and stayed until his death 1985. He was an institution unto himself, and author of two books chronicling the history of GW: Bricks Without Straw: The Evolution of George Washington University (1970) and A Medical Center The Institutional Development of Medical Education in George Washington University (1973). He also wrote The Grand Social Enterprise; A Study of Jeremy Bentham in his Relation to Liberal Nationalism (1932) and A Manual of Ancient History (1937). Kayser was professor of European history from 1917-67 when he assumed the role of professor emeritus. He was also the University Historian from 1962-85.
Elmer Kayser was born in August 27, 1896 in Georgetown, D.C., attended Western High School (now the Duke Ellington School of the Arts), and received a B.A. (1917) and M.A. (1918), and a Ph.D. from Columbia University (1932). During his incredible seventy-one year tenure with the University, he held various administrative offices, among them Secretary of the University, 1918-27, Dean of University Students, 1930-62, and President of the General Alumni Association of GW, 1950-53. He was given a Distinguished Alumni Achievement award in 1941 and awarded and honorary Doctor of Laws in 1948. His activities outside of academia included radio commentator on foreign affairs during World War II, historian of the National Capital Sesquicentennial Commission, and member of the governing boards of Mount Vernon College, the National Cathedral School, the nurses' school committee of Emergency Hospital and Central Dispensary and St. Elizabeth's Hospital. Elmer Kayser served for more than twenty-five years as vice-chairman of the board of the Mount Vernon Seminary (now the Mount Vernon Campus of GW), and received an honorary degree from that institution in 1975. The Elmer Louis Kayser endowed Professorship in History was established in 1983, with more than 1,000 alumni, faculty, staff and friends contributing gifts in excess of $500,000 needed to establish it. Kayser was also a recipient of the George Washington Award at GW in 1977, given "in special recognition to those people who have made The George Washington University a better place to be."
Elmer Kayser died April 28, 1985 in Washington, D.C.
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include correspondence, course lectures, notes, notes on fraternities, speeches, student papers, publications, Mt. Vernon Seminary materials, WTOP Radio "Today in History" broadcasts, professional association memberships, photographs, a video cassette, and two framed pieces of realia. The materials range in date from 1824-1985. These items all relate to the personal and professional life of Elmer Kayser.
Collection Organization
Organized into four series: George Washington University related documentation; Professional papers; Personal papers; and Correspondence, writtings, and records.
Speeches; Washington (D.C.); Education; Photographs; Courses and lectures; Commencement ceremonies -- Washington (D.C.); Greek letter societies; United States; George Washington University--Alumni and alumnae; American Association of University Professors; American Historical Association; Collier, William Miller; Kayser, Elmer Louis; George Washington University--History; Mount Vernon Seminary
- George Washington University related documentation, 1917-1961; MS0245 Series 1; 12.5 Linear feet (Box 25, Box 24, Box 23, Box 22, Box 21, Box 7, Box 8, Box 5, Box 6, Box 3, Box 4, Box 1, Box 2, Box 19, Box 17, Box 18, Box 16, Box 20, Box 15, Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 12, Box 13, Box 14)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains correspondence, lecture notes and handouts, committee files, publication data, and speeches. The material covers the years 1917-61. Much of this material relates to Dr. Kayser's various roles at the University. These posts included among others Secretary of the University, University Marshal, Dean of Students, and University Historian. The records also include some of the work he performed while serving on fourteen University committees.
  - University Marshal, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General Alumni Association, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Alumni Association, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Secretary of the University, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Acting Executive Officer, Department of History, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - University Historian, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - University Historian, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - University Historian, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - University Historian, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - University Historian: History of Columbian University,(Luther Rice), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dean of Students: Orientation, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Deanship, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Deanship: Smith/Quinlan case, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Deanship: Smith/ Quinlan case, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dean's Annual Reports, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Awards and Honors, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Awards and Honors, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chapel, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Consulting, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Commencement, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Committees, 1935-1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Committee for the Centennial Celebration of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Committee for the acquisition fo Gilbert Stuart portrait, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Committees (faculty cooperation), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Public Assemblies Ceremonies Committee, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - School of Government Committee, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - School of Government Committee, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Selection Committee for President, 1921 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Committee on Student Life, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Graduate Council, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Peace Convocation Committee, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee, Hospital Campaign, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - History Committee, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Faculty Organizations, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Narrative (Prepared for a narrator and two voices), undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Leisure Time Facilities Committee, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Women's Activities, building funds (Faculty Follies), undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - General correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - General correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - General correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence (general), undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 50th year anniversary of (teaching), undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Civic Associations, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Department of Health MD/VA, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - General correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - General correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - General correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - General correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - General correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - General correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - General correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, from student body, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, William M. Collier, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, Dean of Faculties, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Government Agencies, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Metzerrott Scholarship, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Public Schools, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Public Schools:F.D.R. High, 06/23/1958 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Special/Foreign Students, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, School of Medicine, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, Virginia Polytechnic (Religious Emphasis Committee), undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence (general), undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Exams from various courses, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Exams from various courses, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Exams from various courses, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Grade books from various courses, 1917-1959 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Grade books from various courses, 1917-1959 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Grade books from various courses, 1917-1959 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Grade books from various courses, 1917-1959 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Grade books from various courses, 1917-1959 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Grade books from various courses, 1917-1959 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Grade books from various courses, 1917-1959 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Grade books from various courses, 1917-1959 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Courses: Grade Books, 1959-1961 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Courses: Grade Books, 1962-1967 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Courses: Handout, World War II, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Courses/Lectures: History 192, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Courses/Lectures: History 191, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Courses/Lectures: History 192, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Courses/Lectures: History 191, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Courses/Lectures, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Lectures: History F.W., 10/29/1935 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Lectures, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Doctoral Questions and Reading Lists, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Courses/Lectures: Interdict and Excommunication, undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Course Examinations: History, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Courses: Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Course Notes: History 191,192, 1960-1961 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Course notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Course notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Course notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Course notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Course notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Courses: Notes (Cleopatra), undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Courses: Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Course notes for Current History, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Course notes for Current History, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Course notes for Current History, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Course notes for Current History, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Course notes for Current History, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Course notes for Current History, undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Course notes for Current History, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Course notes for Current History, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Course notes for Current History, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Course notes for Current History, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Course notes for Current History, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Course notes for Current History, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Course notes for Current History, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Course notes for Current History, undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Course Notes: Nationalism, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Course Notes: History 109, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Course Notes: History, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Course Notes: History 109-110, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Course Notes: History 109, undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Course Notes: History 109/110, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Course Notes: History 40, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Course Notes: History 40B, undated (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Course Exams: History 40B, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Course Notes: Modern History, History 38B, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Course Notes: Ferrero &. Barbagallo, (1921), The Russian Revolution, (1922); Hellenic History, (1922), undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Course Notes: French Revolution from the Thermidorean Period, 1921 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Course Notes: Modern Education, 1921 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Course Notes: History 38, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Course Notes: Intellectual History of the Middle Ages, 1947-1959 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Course Notes: Modern European Diplomatic History, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Course Notes: Late Medieval Civilization, 1100 - --1300 II, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Course Notes: Notes On Modern Europe from the French Revolution, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Course Notes: Europe since 1815, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Course Notes: Italian Renaissance/Middle Ages, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Course Notes: Miscellaneous, undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Course Notes: Miscellaneous, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Course Notes: Modern Europe, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Course Notes: Monroe's Source: Fragments of the Law of the Twelve Tables, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Course Notes: Reformation History, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Course Notes: History 120, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Course Notes: History 21, undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Course Notes: Medieval Romances/The Troubadours, undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Course notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Course notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Course notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Course notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Course notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Course notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Course Notes: Renaissance Book II, Summer School, 1922 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Course Notes: Renaissance in Italy, Summer School, 1926 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Course Notes Political Sciences Cases, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Course Notes: History (A) Essays on Nationalism, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Course Notes: History (B) Essays on Nationalism, pt.2, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Course Notes: Business English I, undated (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Course Notes, prepared by M.F.J. Brunow, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Course Notes English 1OB, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Course Notes: Speech, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous course notes, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous course notes, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous course notes, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous course notes, undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Course Notes: History 119, undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Course Notes: Roman History, Modern History, 1923 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Course Notes, undated (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Course Notes: Modern Europe, undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Course Notes: Current History (Stalingrad Period), undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Course Notes: Greece, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Course Notes: Miscellaneous, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Course Notes: History 119, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Course Notes: History 120, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - GWU Development Office, 1963 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Elmer Louis Kayser Prize in History, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Enosinian Society, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Exhibits, undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Faculty Club, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Faculty Reports, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Fraternities: ALPHA PHI, undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Fraternities: DELTA PHI EPSILON, undated (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Fraternities: KAPPA TAU OMEGA, undated (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Fraternities: OMICRON DELTA KAPPA, undated (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Fraternities: PHI ALPHA THETA, undated (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Fraternities: PI LAMBDA THETA, undated (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Fraternities: SIGMA ALPHA EPSILON, undated (Box 16, Folder 18)
  - Fraternities: SIGMA NU PHI, undated (Box 16, Folder 19)
  - Fraternities: SIGMA PHI EPSILON, undated (Box 16, Folder 20)
  - Fraternities: THETA UPSILON OMEGA, undated (Box 16, Folder 21)
  - Fraternities: National Interfraternity Conference, undated (Box 16, Folder 22)
  - Inaugural, Thomas Henry Carroll, 1961 (Box 16, Folder 23)
  - Library, Donations to Gelman, Correspondence, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Luther Rice Society, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Publications, Abstracts, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Published book reviews, undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Published book reviews, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Published book reviews, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Published book reviews, undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Published book reviews, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Published book reviews, undated (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - 0Published book reviews, undated (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - 1Published book reviews, undated (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - 2Published book reviews, undated (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - 3Published book reviews, undated (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - 4Published book reviews, undated (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Publications: Journal Articles, undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Publications: Journal Articles/World Affairs, 1955-1958 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Publications: World Affairs, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Publications: World Affairs, 1949-1950 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Publications: World Affairs, 1950-1951 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Publications: Journal Articles/World Affairs, 1955-1958 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Publications: Eisenhower years, Foreign Policy, undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Publications: Monographs, undated (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Publications: Man and the Western World, undated (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Publications of Elmer Kayser: Manual of Ancient History, undated (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Publications: Manual of Ancient History, undated (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Publications, Monographs: A Manual of Ancient History, undated (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Publications, Monographs: Twentieth Century History, undated (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Publications of Elmer Kayser: Nationalism, undated (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Publications, Monographs: A Medical Center (Mss. Folder #5), undated (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Publications, Monographs: A Medical Center (Mss. Folder #4), undated (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Publications, Monographs: A Medical Center (Mss. Folder #3), undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Publications, Monographs: A Medical Center (Mss. Folder #2), undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Publications, Monographs: A Medical Center (Mss. Folder #1), undated (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Publications, Monographs: A Medical Center, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Publications: Log and Ms. Proof for A Medical Center, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Publications, Monographs (1): A Medical Center, undated (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Publications, Monographs (2): A Medical Center, undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Publications: Journal Articles, undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Publications: Nationalism, undated (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Publications: Grand Social Enterprise, undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Publications: Grand Social Enterprise (with Copyright), undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Publications: Contemporary Europe, undated (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Publications: Copyrights, undated (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Monographs from publication Bricks Without a Straw, undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Monographs from publication Bricks Without a Straw, undated (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Publications of Elmer L. Kayser in Coronet, 1949-1950 (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - Publications of Elmer L. Kayser in Coronet, 1949-1950 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Publications: Poetry, undated (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Retirement Benefits, undated (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Lectures, undated (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Speeches of E. L. Kayser, undated (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Speeches of E. L. Kayser, undated (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Speeches of E. L. Kayser, undated (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Speeches of E. L. Kayser, undated (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Speeches of E. L. Kayser, undated (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Speeches / E. L. Kayser, undated (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Speeches of E.L. Kayser, undated (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Speeches of E.L. Kayser, undated (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Speeches / E.L. Kayser, 1949-1950 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Speeches/E. L. Kayser, undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Speeches: Saturday Forenoon Sessions (History 39-40), Students, incidents, professors recalled, 1971 (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - Speeches: Life Officers Investment Seminar, undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Office of Student Activities, undated (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Student Term Papers, undated (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Student term papers and reports, undated (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Student term papers and reports, undated (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Student term papers and reports, undated (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Student term papers and reports, undated (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Lecture recordings, 1964; .25 Linear Feet (Box 44)
- Professional papers, 1921-1973; MS0245 Series 2; 2.5 Linear feet (Box 29, Box 28, Box 27, Box 26, Box 30)
  This series contains correspondence, radio broadcasts, membership records, and committee records for professional associations. These materials date from 1921-73. These professional papers deal with professional groups in the social sciences that Kayser was associated with during his career. These organizations include the American Association of Collegiate Registrars, American Association of University Professors, and American Historical Association. This series also contains information related to the Mt. Vernon Seminary where Kayser worked as a professor.
  - Mt. Vernon Seminary, 1946-1949 (Box 26, Folder 1)